<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To His Highnesse the Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland the humble addresses of Menasseh ben Israel, a divine, and doctor of physick, in behalfe of the Jewish nation.</title>
            <author>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M379</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224573</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12639294</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12639294</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64987</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64987)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 697:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To His Highnesse the Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland the humble addresses of Menasseh ben Israel, a divine, and doctor of physick, in behalfe of the Jewish nation.</title>
                  <author>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jews --  England.</term>
               <term>Jewish diaspora.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64987:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64987:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO HIS HIGHNESSE THE LORD PROTECTOR OF THE <hi>COMMON-WEALTH OF</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <p>THE HUMBLE ADDRESSES OF MENASSEH Ben Iſrael, <hi>a Divine, and Doctor of PHYSICK, in behalfe of the Jewiſh Nation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="address">
            <pb facs="tcp:64987:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64987:2"/>
            <head>TO His Highneſſe the Lord PROTECTOR OF THE Common-wealth of ENGLAND, SCOTLAND, and IRELAND <hi>The Humble Addreſſes of</hi> Menaſſeh Ben Iſrael, <hi>a Divine and Doctor of Phyſick, in behalf of the Jewiſh Nation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ive me leave, at ſuch a juncture of time, to your Highneſſe, in a ſtyle and manner fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to us <hi>Jewes</hi> and our condition. It is a thing moſt certain, that the great God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Creator of Heaven and Earth, doth give &amp; take away Dominions and Empires, according to his own pleaſure; exalting ſome, &amp; overthrowing others: who, ſeeing he hath the hearts of Kings in his hand; he eaſily moves them whitherſoever himſelf pleaſeth, to put in execution his Divine Commands. This, my Lord, appears moſt evidently out of thoſe words of <hi>Daniel,</hi> where he, rendring thanks unto God, for revealing unto him that prodigious Dream of <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> doth ſay: <hi>Thou that removeſt Kings, and ſets up Kings.</hi> And elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>To the end the living might know, that the Highest hath dominion in Mans Kingdome, and giveth the ſame to whom he pleaſe.</hi> Of the very ſame mind are <hi>Thalmudiſts</hi> likewiſe, affirming that a good Government, or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, is a Heavenly Gift, and that there is no Governor, but is firſt called by God unto that dignity: &amp; this they prove from that paſſage of <hi>Exodus: Behold I have called Bazale'l by name,</hi> &amp;c. all things being governed by Divine Providence, God diſpenſing rewards unto Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and puniſhment unto Vices, according to his owne
<pb facs="tcp:64987:3"/>good Will. This the Examples of great Monarchs make good; eſpecially of ſuch, who have afflicted the people of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> For none hath ever afflicted them, who hath not been by ſome ominous <hi>Exit,</hi> moſt heavily puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God Almighty; as is manifeſt from the Hiſtories of thoſe Kings, <hi>Pharaoh, Nebuchadnezar, Antiochus, Epiphanius, Pompey,</hi> &amp; others. And on the contrary, none ever was a Benefactor to that people, &amp; cheriſhed them in their Countries, who thereupon hath not preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun very much to flouriſh. In ſo much that the Oracle to <hi>Abraham (I will bleſse them that bleſse thee, and curſe them that curſe thee)</hi> ſeemeth yet daily to have its accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment. Hence I, one of the leaſt among the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſince by experience I have found, that through Gods great bounty toward us, many conſiderable and eminent perſons both for Piety &amp; Power, are moved with ſincere and inward pitty and compaſſion towards us, &amp; do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us concerning the approaching deliverance of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> could not but for my ſelf, and in the behalf of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men, make this my humble addreſs to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp; beſeech you for Gods ſake, that ye would, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that Piety &amp; Power wherein you are eminent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond others, vouchſafe to grant, that the Great &amp; Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name of the Lord our God may be extolled, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly worſhipped and praiſed by us through all the bounds of this Common-wealth; &amp; to grant us place in your Countrey, that we may have our Synagogues, and free exerciſe of our Religion. I nothing doubting, but that your Clemency will eaſily grant this moſt equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition of ours. Pagans have of old, out of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the God of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and the eſteem they had to his people granted moſt willingly free liberty, even to apoſtated <hi>Jewes;</hi> as <hi>Onias</hi> the High Prieſt, to build ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Temple in their Countrey, like unto that at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> how much more then may we, that are not Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate
<pb facs="tcp:64987:3"/>or runagate <hi>Jewes,</hi> hope it from your Highneſſe and your Chriſtian Council, ſince you have ſo great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of, and adore the ſame one onely God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with us. Beſides, it increaſes our confidence of your bounty towards us, in that ſo ſoon as ever the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of that moſt wiſhed-for liberty, that ye were a thinking to grant us, was made known unto our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men; I, in the name of my Nation, the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that live in <hi>Holland,</hi> did congratulate and entertain their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, the Ambaſſadors of <hi>England;</hi> who were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in our Synagogue with as great pomp &amp; applauſe, Hymns and cheerfulneſſe of mind, as ever any Soveraign Prince was. For our people did in their own minds pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, that the Kingly Government being now changed into that of a Common-wealth, the ancient hatred to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, would alſo be changed into good will: that thoſe rigorous Laws (if any there be yet extant, made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Kings) againſt ſo innocent a people, would hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily be repealed. So that we hope now for better from your gentleneſſe, and goodneſſe, ſince, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your Gouernment of this Common-wealth, your Highneſſe hath profeſſed much reſpect, and favour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. Wherefore I humbly entreat your Higneſſe, that you would with a gracious eye have regard unto us, and our Petition, and grant unto us, as you have done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others, free exerciſe of our Religion, that we may have our Synagogues, and keep our own publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as our brethren doe in <hi>Italy, Germany, Poland,</hi> and many other places, and we ſhall pray for the happineſſe and Peace of this your much renowned &amp; puiſſant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:64987:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A DECLARATION TO THE Common-wealth of ENGLAND, BY</hi> Rabbi Menaſſeh Ben <hi>ISRAEL,</hi> ſhewing the Motives of his coming into England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſome years ſince often perceived that in this Nation, God hath a People, that is very tender hearted, and well wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our ſore afflicted Nation; Yea, I my ſelf having ſome Experience thereof, in divers Eminent perſons, excelling both in Piety and Learning: I thought with my ſelf, I ſhould do no ſmall ſervice to my own Nation, as alſo to the People and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Common-wealth, if by humble addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the late Honourable Parliament, I might obtain a ſafe. Conduct once to tranſport my ſelf thither. Which I having done, and according to my deſire, received a moſt kinde and ſatisfactory Anſwer, I now am come. And to the end all Men may know the true Motives and Intent of this my coming, I ſhall briefly comprehend and deliver them in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt and Formoſt,</hi> my Intention is to try, if by Gods good hand over me, I may obtain here for my Nation the Liberty of a free and publick Synagogue, wherein we may daily call upon the Lord our God, that once he
<pb facs="tcp:64987:4"/>may be pleaſed to remember his Mercies and Promiſes done to our Fore fathers, forgiving our treſpaſſes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring us once again into our fathers Inheritance; and beſides to ſue alſo for a bleſſing upon this Nation, and People of <hi>England,</hi> for receiving us into their boſomes, and comforting <hi>Sion</hi> in her diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>My <hi>ſecond</hi> Motive is, becauſe the opinion of many Chriſtians and mine doe concurre herein, that we both believe that the reſtoring time of our Nation into their Native Countrey, is very near at hand; I believing more particularly, that this reſtauration cannot be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe words of <hi>Daniel</hi> Chap. 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. be firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, when he ſaith, <hi>And when the diſperſion of the Holy people ſhall be compleated in all places, then ſhall all theſe things be compleated:</hi> ſignifying therewith, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all be fulfilled, the People of God muſt be firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed into all places &amp; Countreys of the World. Now we know, how our Nation at the preſent is ſpread all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and hath its ſeat and dwelling in the moſt flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts of all the Kingdomes, and Countreys of the Worlds, as well in <hi>America,</hi> as in the other three parts thereof; except onely in this conſiderable and mighty Iſland. And therefore this remains onely in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before the <hi>MESSIA</hi> come and reſtore our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that firſt we muſt have our ſeat here likewiſe.</p>
            <p>My <hi>thira</hi> Motive is grounded on the profit that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this Common-wealth is to reap, if it ſhall vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to receive us; for thence, I hope, there will follow a great bleſſing from God upon them, and a very abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant trading into, and from all parts of the World, not onely without prejudice to the Engliſh Nation, but for their profit, both in Importation, and Exportation of goods. Yet if any ſhall doubt hereof, I truſt their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity towards the people of God, will ſatisfie them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they ſhall read the enſuing Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:64987:5"/>The <hi>fourth</hi> Motive of my coming hither, is, my ſincere affection to this Common-wealth, by reaſon of ſo many Worthy, Learned, &amp; Pious men in this Nation, whoſe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe &amp; Piety I have experience of: hoping to finde the like affection in all the People generally, the more, becauſe I alwaies have, both by writing and deeds, profeſſed much inclination to this Common-wealth; and that I perſwade my ſelf they will be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of that Command of the Lord our God, who ſo highly recommends unto all men the <hi>love of ſtrangers;</hi> much more to thoſe that profeſſe their good affection to them. For this I deſire all may be confident of, that I am not come to make any diſturbance, or to move any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes about matters of Religion; but onely to live with my Nation in the fear of the Lord, under the ſhadow of your protection, whiles we expect with you <hi>the hope of Iſrael</hi> to be revealed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64987:5"/>
            <head>How Profitable The Nation of the Iewes are.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree</hi> things, if it pleaſe your Highneſſe, there are that make a ſtrange <hi>Nation</hi> wel-beloved amongſt the Natives of a land where they dwell; and on the contrary, <hi>three</hi> things that make them hatefull. viz. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,</hi> they may receive from them; <hi>Fidelity</hi> they hold towards their Princes; and the <hi>Noblenes</hi> and purety of their blood. Now when I ſhall have made good, that all <hi>theſe three</hi> things are found in the <hi>Iewiſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> I ſhall certainly perſuade your Highneſſe, that with a favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eye, (Monarchy being changed into a Republicq) you ſhall be pleaſed to receive againe the Nation of the Iews, who in time paſt lived in that Iſland: but by, I know not what, falſe Informations, were cruelly handled and baniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Profit</hi> is a moſt powerfull motive, and which all the World preferres before all other things: and therefore wee ſhall handle that point firſt.</p>
            <p>It is a thing confirmed, that merchandicing is, as it were, the proper profeſſion of the Nation of the Iews. I attribute this in the firſt place, to the particular Providence and mercy of God towards his people: for having baniſhed them from their own Countrey, yet not from his Protection, hee hath given them, as it were, a naturall inſtinct, by which they might not onely gain what was neceſſary for their need, but that they ſhould alſo thrive in Riches and poſſeſſions; whereby they ſhould not onely become gracious to their Princes and Lords, but that they ſhould be invited by others to come and dwell in their Lands.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64987:6"/>Moreover, it cannot be denyed, but that neceſſity ſtirres up a mans ability and induſtry; and that it gives him great incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by all meanes to trie the favour of Fortune.</p>
            <p>Beſides, ſeeing it is no Wiſedome for them to endeavour the gaining of Land and other immovable goods, and ſo to impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon their poſſeſſions here, where their perſons are ſubject to ſo many caſualities, baniſhments and peregrinations; they are forced to uſe marchandizing untill that time, when they ſhall returne to their owne Country, that then as God hath promiſed by de Prophet Zachary, <hi>There ſhall be found no more any merchant amongſt them in the Houſe of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From that very thing we have ſaid, there riſeth an infallible Profit, commodity and gain to all thoſe Princes in whoſe Lands they dwell above all other ſtrange Nations whatſoever, as experience by divers <hi>Reaſons</hi> doth confirme.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Iewes, having no oportunity to live in their own Country, to till the Lands or other like employments, give themſelves wholy unto merchandizing, and for contriving new Inventions, no Nation almoſt going beyond them. And ſo 't is obſerved, that whereſoever they go to dwell, there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the Traficq begins to floriſh. Which may be ſeen in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, eſpecially in Ligorne, which having been but a very ignoble and inconſiderable City, is at this time, by the great concourſe of people, one of the moſt famous places of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique of whole Italy.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the Inventor of the famous <hi>Scala de Spalatro</hi> (the moſt firme and ſolid Traficq of Venice) was a Iew, who by this his Invention tranſported the Negotiation from a great part of the Levant into that Citie.</p>
            <p>Even that very ſame is ſeene likewiſe at this day in Nizza, and in other infinite places more, both in Europe and Aſia.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Nation of the Iews is diſperſed throughout the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64987:6"/>whole world, it being a chaſtiſement that God hath layd upon them for their Idolatries, Deut. 28.69. Ezech. 20.23. Nehem. 1.8. Pſal. 107.27. as likewayes by contrary fortunes their families ſuffer the ſame ſhip wrack.</p>
            <p>Now in this diſperſion our Fore-fathers flying from the Spaniſh Inquiſition, ſome of them came in Holland, others got into Italy, and others betooke themſelves in Aſia; and ſo eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they credit one another; and by that meanes they draw the Negotiation where-ever they are; wherewith all of them mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing and having perfect knowledge of all the kinds of Moneys, Diamants, Cochinil, Indigo, Wines, oyle, and other Commodities, that ſerve from place to place; eſpecially hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing correſpondence with their friends and kinds-folke, whoſe language they underſtand; they do abundantly enrich the Lands and Countries of ſtrangers, where they live, not onely with what is requiſite and neceſſary for the life of man, but alſo what may ſerve for ornament to his civill condition. Of which <hi>Traficq,</hi> there ariſeth ordinarily <hi>Five</hi> important benefits.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The augmentation of the Publiq Tolls and Gabels, at their coming in and going out of the place.</item>
               <item>2. The tranſporting and bringing in of marchandiſes from remote Countries.</item>
               <item>3. The affording of Materials in great plenty for all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaniqs; as Wooll, Leather and Hides, and ſuch like Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize.</item>
               <item>4. The venting and exportation of ſo many kinds of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifactures.</item>
               <item>5. The Commerce and reciprocall Negotiation at Sea, which is the ground of Peace between neighbour Nations, and of great profit to their own fellow-citizens.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">III. This reaſon is the more ſtrengthened, when we ſee, that not onely the Iewiſh Nation dwelling in Holland and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64987:7"/>Italy, traficq with their owne ſtocke, but alſo with the richeſſe of many others of their owne Nation, friends, kinds-men and acquaintance, which not withſtanding live in Spaine, and ſend unto them their moneys and goods, which they hold in their hands, and content themſelves with a very ſmall portion of their eſtate, to the end they may be ſecure and free from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that might happen unto them, in caſe they ſhould fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they yoke of the Inquiſition; whence not onely their goods, but oftentimes alſo their lives are endangered.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The love that men ordinarily beare to their owne Country, and the deſire they have to end their lives, where they had their begining, is the cauſe, that moſt ſtrangers having got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten richeſſe where they are in a forain land; are commonly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a deſire to returne to their natif ſoil, and there peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to enjoy their eſtate; ſo that as they were a help to the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they lived, and negotiated while they remained there; ſo when they depart from thence, they carry all away, and ſpoile them of their wealth: tranſporting all into their owne native Country: But with the Jewes the caſe is farre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent; for where the Iewes are once kindly receaved, they make a firm reſolution never to depart from thence, ſeeing they have no proper place of their owne: and ſo they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with their goods in the Cities where they live, a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall benefit to all payments. Which reaſons do clearly proove, that it being the property of Citizens in populous and rich countries, to ſeeke their reſt and eaſe with buying lands and faire póſſeſſion of which they live: many of them hating commerce, aſpire to Titles and Dignities: that of all ſtrangers, in whoſe hands ordinarily Trafique is found, there are none ſo profitable and beneficiall to the place where they trade and live, as is the Nation of the Iewes. And ſeeing amongſt the people of Europe, the chiefeſt richeſſes they poſſeſſe, come
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64987:7"/>from Spaine, thoſe neighbour Nations, where the Iewes ſhall finde liberty to live according to their owne Iudaïcall Lawes, they ſhall moſt eaſily draw that benefit to themſelves by meanes of the induſtry of our Nation, and their mutuall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondance.</p>
            <p>From hence (if it pleaſe your Highnes) it reſults; that the Jewiſh Nation, though ſcattered through the whole World, are not therefore a deſpiſable people, but as a Plant worthy to be planted in the whole world, received into populous Cities: who ought to plant them in thoſe places, which are moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from danger; being trees of moſt ſavory fruit and profit, to be alwayes moſt favoured with Lawes and Priviledges; or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, ſecured and defended by Armes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> An Exemple of this we have in our times. His Majeſty, the Illuſtrious King of Danemarck, invited them with ſpeciall Priviledges into Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckſtadt: the Duke of Savoy into Niſa of Provence; and the Duke of Modina in Retio, allowing them ſuch conditions and benefices, the like never were preſented unto them by any other Prince, as appeareth by the copy of thoſe Priviledges, which I have in my hands. But ſuppoſing it would be a matter of too large extention, if I ſhould make a relation of all the places under whoſe Princes the Iewes live, I will onely ſpeaké briefly of the two Tribes Iudah and Benjamin: Theſe in India in Cochin have 4 Synagogues, one part of theſe Iewes being there of a white colour, and three of a tawny; theſe being moſt favoured by the King. In the yeare 1640. dyed Samuel Caſtoel, Gouvernour of the City, and Agent for the King, and David Caſtoel his ſonne ſucceeded in his place. In Perſia there is a great number of Iewes, and they live indifferent freely: there are alſo amongſt them that are in favour and great reſpect by the King, and who live there very bravely. Some years paſt, there was Elhazar Huza, the Viceroy, and now there is David
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64987:8"/>Ian, if yet he be living. In the year 1636. the Saltan Amarat tooke in Bagdad, and puting all to the ſword, he commanded that they ſhould not touch the Iewes, nor their houſes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, he freed them from one half of the tribut they were wont to pay to the Perſian.</p>
            <p>But the chiefeſt place where the Iewes live, is the Turkiſh Empire, where ſome of them live in great eſtate, even in the Court of the Grand Turke at Conſtantinople, by reaſon there is no Viceroy, or Gouvernour, or Baſſa, which hath not a Iew to manage his affaires, and to take care for his eſtate: Hence it cometh, that in ſhort time they grow up to be Lords of great revenus, and they moſt frequently bend the minds of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones to moſt weighty affaires in gouvernment.</p>
            <p>The greateſt Viceroy of whole Europe is the Baſſa of Egypt; this Baſſa always takes to him, by ordre of the Kingdome, a lew with the title of Zaraf-Baſſa <hi>(Threſurer)</hi> viz. of all the Revenus of that gouvernment, who receaves purſes full of money, ſeals them, and then ſends them to the King. This man in a ſhort time grows very rich, for that by his hands as being next to the Baſſa, the 24 Gouvernments of that Empire are ſould and given, and all other buſſineſſes menaged. At preſent he that poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this place, is called S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Abraham Alhula. The number of the Iews living in this Kingdome of the Great Turke, is very great, and amounts to many Millions. In Conſtantinople alone there are 48 Synagogues, and in Salaminque 36, and more then foureſcore thouſand ſoules in theſe two Cities alone.</p>
            <p>The firſt King gave them great priviledges, which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy untill this day: for beſides the liberty, they have every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, of trading with open ſhops, of bearing any Office and poſſeſſing of any goods, both mooveable and immooveable, he yet graunted them power to judge all Civill cauſes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their own Lawes amongſt themſelves. Moreover they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64987:8"/>are exempted from going to Warres, and that ſouldiers ſhould be quartered in their houſes, and that Iuſtice ſhould take no place upon the death of any one that left no heir to his Eſtate.</p>
            <p>In all which they are preferred before the naturall Turkes themſelves. For which cauſe they pay in ſome Cities to the King three Patacons, and in others two and a half by the pole.</p>
            <p>In this eſtate ſome of the Iewes have growne to great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; as Joſeph Naſino, unto whom Amatus Luſitanus dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his fifth and ſixth Centuriae, was by Sultan Solime made Duke of Maccia, Earle of Andro, Seignor of Millo, and the ſeaven Iſlands: And Iacob Ben-Iaes by Sultan Amurat, was made Gouvernour of the Tiberiades: ſo likewiſe others were exalted to very great and eminent Dignities: as was that Selo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Rofe, that was ſent for Ambaſſador at Venice, where he confirmed the laſt Peace with Amurat. In Germany, there lives alſo a great multitude of Iews, eſpecially at Prague, Vienna and Franckfurt, very much favoured by the moſt mild and moſt gracious Emperours, but deſpiſed of the people, being a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not very finely garniſhed by reaſon of their vile cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: yet notwithſtanding there is not wanting amongſt them perſons of great quality. The Emperour Matthias made Noble both Mardochai Mairel, and Ferdinando Jacob Bar Seba.</p>
            <p>But yet a greater number of Iews are found in the Kingdome of Poland, Pruſſia and Lethuania, under which Monarchy they have the Iuriſdiction to judge amongſt themſelves all cauſes, both Criminal and Civil; and alſo great and famous Academies of their owne. The chief Cities where the Nation liveth, are Lublin and Cracow, where there is a Iew, called Iſaac Iecells, who built a Synagogue, which ſtood him in one hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Francs, and is worth many tons of gold. There is in this place ſuch infinite number of Iewes, that although the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaques in the late warres have killed of them above one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64987:9"/>and foureſcore thouſand; yet it is ſuſtained that they are yet at this day as innumerable as thoſe were that came out of Egypt. In that Kingdome the whole Negotiation is in the hand of the Iews, the reſt of the Chriſtians are either all Noble-men, or Ruſtiques and kept as ſlaves.</p>
            <p>In Italy they are generally protected by all the Princes: their principall reſidence is in the moſt famous Citie of Venice; ſo that in that ſame City alone they poſſeſſe about 1400 Houſes; and are uſed there with much courtoiſy and clemency. Many alſo live in Padoa and Verona; others in Mantua, and alſo many in Rome it ſelf. Finally they are ſcattered here and there in the chief places of Italy, and do live there with many ſpeciall priviledges.</p>
            <p>In the Gouvernment of the great Duke of Tuſcany, they are by that Prince moſt graciouſly and bountifully dealt with, having power from him graunted, to have their Iudicatory by themſelves, and to judge in all matters, both Civill and Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; beſides many other Priviledges, whereof I my ſelf have the Copies in hand. The rich and illuſtrious families that flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in theſe Countries are many, viz. The Thoraces, who being three Brethren, ſhared betwixt them above 700 thouſand Crownes. In Ferrara were the Viles, whoſe ſtock was above 200 thouſand Crownes. The Lord Ioſeph de Fano, Marquis de Villependi, was a man much reſpected of all the Princes in Italy, and was called by them, The Peace-maker and appeaſer of all troubles; becauſe he, by his auctority and entremiſe, was uſed to appeaſe all troubles and ſtrife riſing amongſt them. Don Daniel Rodrigues, becauſe of his prudency and other good qualities, was ſent in the year 1589 from the moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Senat of Venice into Dalmatia, to appeaſe thoſe tumults and ſcandals given by the Uſquoquibs in Cliſſa: which he moſt manly effected, and cauſed all the women and children,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64987:9"/>that were kept clooſe priſonners, to be ſet at liberty, brought alſo to an happy iſſue many other things of great moment, for which he was ſent. Alphonſo II. the Duke of Ferrara, ſent alſo for his Ambaſſador to the Imperiall Majeſty, one Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham de Bondi, to pay and diſcharge Inveſtiture of the States of Modena and Reggio. The Prince of Saſol and the Marquis of Scandia likewiſe, had to their Factors men of our Nation.</p>
            <p>In the King dome of Barbary, there lives alſo a great number of Iewes, who-ever cruelly and baſely uſed by that Barbarous Nation, except at Marrocco, the Court and Kings houſe, where they have their Naguid or Prince that gouverns them, and is their Iudge, and is called at this day, Seignor Moſeh Palache: and before him was in the ſame Court, that Noble family Ruthes, that had power and Iuriſdiction of all kinde of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, onely life and death excepted.</p>
            <p>In the Low-Countries alſo, the Iewes are received with great Charity and Benevolency, and eſpecially in this moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned City of Amſterdam, where there are no leſſe then 400 Families; and how great a trading and Negotiation they draw to that City, experience doth ſufficiently witneſſe. They have there no leſſe then three hundred houſes of their own, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a good part of the Weſt and Eaſt-Indian Compagnies; and beſides have yet to ſet forth their Traficq ſuch a ſtock, that for ſetting a ſide, onely one duit of every pound flamiſh for all kind of commodities that enter, and again as much for all what goes out of this towne, and what beſides we pay yearly of the rents we get from the Eaſt-Indian Compagnie to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe and ſuſtenance of the poore of our Synagogue, that very money amounts ordinarily every year, unto the ſumme very neare of 12000 Franks; whereby you may eaſely conceive what a mighty ſtock it is they trade with, and what a profit they needs muſt bring into this City.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64987:10"/>In Hambourg likewiſe, a moſt famous City of Holſace in Germany, there lives alſo a hundred families, protected by the Magiſtrat, though moleſted by the people. There reſides Sr. Duarck Mines d'Acoſta, Reſident for his Majeſty the King of Portugal: Gabriel Gomes, Agent for his Majeſty the King of Danemarck: David de Lima, a Ieweller, for the ſame his Majeſty; and Emanuël Boccaro Roſales, created by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour a Noble-man and a Count Palatin.</p>
            <p>In all theſe places the Iewes live (in a manner) all of them Merchants, and that without any prejudice at all to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives: For the Natives, and thoſe eſpecially that are moſt rich, they build themſelves houſes and Palaces, buy Lands and firme goods, aime at Titles and Dignities, and ſo ſeeke their reſt and contentement that way: But as for the Iewes, they aſpire at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but to preferre themſelves in their way of marchandize; and ſo employing their <hi>Capitals,</hi> they ſend forth the benefit of their labour amongſt many and ſundry of the Natives, which they, by the traficq of their Negotiation, do enrich. From whence it's eaſy to judge of the profit that Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths do reap, by giving liberty of Religion to the Iewes, and gathering them by ſome ſpeciall priviledges into their Countries: as Trees that bring forth ſuch excellent fruits.</p>
            <p>So that if one Prince, ill adviſed, driveth them out of his Land, yet another invites them to his, and ſhews them favour: Wherein we may ſee the prophety of Iacob fulfilled in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>The ſtaffe (to ſupport him) ſhall not depart from Iacob, untill Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias ſhall come.</hi> And this ſhall ſuffice concerning the Profit of the Iewiſh Nation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64987:10"/>
            <head>How Faithfull The Nation of the Iewes are.</head>
            <p>THe Fidelity of Vaſſals and Subjects, is a thing that Princes much moſt eſteem off: for there-on, both in Peace and Warre, depends the preſervation of their eſtates. And as for this point, in my opinion, they owe much to the Nation of the Iewes, by reaſon of the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and loyalty they ſhow to all Potentates that receive and protect them in their Countries. For ſetting aſide the Hiſtories of the Ptolomies, Kings of Egypt, who did not truſt the Guard of their perſons, nor the keeping of their Forts, nor the moſt important affaires of their Kingdom to any other Nation with greater ſatiſfaction then to the Iewes; the Wounds of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater ſhewed to Julius Caeſar in token of his loyalty, and the braſen Tables of our Anceſtours amongſt the Romans, are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent witneſſes enough of their fidelity ſhewed unto them.</p>
            <p>In Spaine the Iewes of Burgos, as the Cronicles do declare, moſt generouſly ſhewed the very ſame fidelity in the times of Don Henrique; who having killed his Brother, the King, Don Pedro de Cruël, made himſelf Lord of all his Kingdoms, and brought under his obedience all the Grandos and people of Spaine: Onely the Iewes of Burgos denyed to obey him, and fortified themſelves within the City, ſaying, <hi>That God would never have it, that they ſhould deny obedience to their Naturall Lord Don Pedro, or to his rightfull ſucceſſours.</hi> A conſtancy that the prudent King, Don Henriques, very much eſteemed of, ſaying, that ſuch Vaſſals as thoſe were, by Kings and great men, worthy of much account, ſeeing they held greater reſpect to the fidelity <hi>they ought to their King, although conquered and dead, than to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64987:11"/>fortune of the Conquerour:</hi> And a while after, receiving very <hi>honourable conditions, they gave themſelves over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Spaine alſo (as you may ſee in Mariana) many Iewes for the ſame fidelity were appointed Gouvernours of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and Tutors of Noble-mens children, jointly to others of the Nobility upon the death of their Parents.</p>
            <p>The Chronicles of the Xarifes, dedicated to King Philip the ſecond, King of Spaine, alleagues for an exemple of great fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and vertue, how the riſing of the Xarifes againſt the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, their killing and ſpoyling them of the Kingdome, was ſuch a great grief unto Samuel Alvalenſi, one of thoſe baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of Spaine, and much favoured by the king of Fez, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from the houſe of the Morines; that joyning himſelf with other Magiſtrats, and ſubjects of the Morines, arming ſome ſhips and going himſelf Captain over all, he came ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly with 400 men, and fell by night upon the Army of the Xarifes, that were more then 3000 men, beſieging Copta, and without loſing one man, killed of them above 500, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to raiſe the ſiege.</p>
            <p>Many the like Exemples may be brought of times paſt; but for our preſent, and moderne times there is no Exemple ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as in the beſieging of Mantua for the Emperour in the year 1630, where the Iewes fought moſt valiantly, and reſcued it from the Natives. As likewiſe in the Seignory of Braſil, where the ſame thing was done: for one of the ſame Nation, a Dutchman, having delivered the Cape unto the Portugals, there was found in our Nation there not onely loyalty, but alſo ſuch diſcretion, that had they taken their adviſe, the buſines had not ſo proceeded.</p>
            <p>This may be ſeen more clearly yet in their being baniſhed out of Caſtilla, in the dayes of Ferdinand and Iſabella. Their number at that time was ſuppoſed to have bene half a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64987:11"/>of men, amongſt whom were many of great valour and courage (as Don Iſaac Abarbanel, a Counſellor of State, doth relate) and yet amongſt ſo great a number, there was not found any one man, that undertooke to raiſe a party to free themſelves from that moſt miſerable baniſhment. An evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſigne of the proper and naturall reſolution of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of their conſtant obedience to their Princes.</p>
            <p>The ſame affection is confirmed by the inviolable cuſtome of all the Iewes whereſoever they live: for on every Sabbath or feſtivall Day, they everywhere are uſed to pray for the ſafety of all Kings, Princes and Common-wealths, under whoſe juriſdiction they live, of what profeſſion-ſoever: unto which duety they are bound by the Prophets and the Talmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſts; from the Law, as by Ieremy chap. 29. verſ. 7. <hi>Seek the peace of the Citie unto which I have made you to wander: and pray for her unto the Lord, for in her Peace you ſhall enjoy peace.</hi> He ſpeaks of Babylon, where the Jewes at that time were captives. From the Talmud ord. 4. tract. 4. Abodazara pereq. 1. <hi>Pray for the peace of the Kingdome, for unles there were feare of the Kingdome, men would ſwallow one the other alive, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the continuall and never broken Cuſtome of the Iewes whereſoever they are, on the Sabbath-Day, or other ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Feaſts; at which time all the Iewes from all places come together to the Synagogue, after the benediction of the Holy Law, before the Miniſter of the Synagogue bleſſeth the people of the Iewes; with a loud voice he bleſſeth the Prince of the Country under whom they live, that all the Iewes may heare it, and ſay, Amen. The words he uſeth are theſe, as in the printed booke of the Iewes may be ſeen: <hi>He that giveth ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto Kings, and dominion unto Lords, he that delivered his ſervant David from the ſword of the Enemy, he that made a way in the Sea, and a path in the ſtrang waters, bleſſe and keep, preſerve and reſcue, exalt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64987:12"/>and magnify, and lift up higher and higher, our Lord.</hi> [And then he names, the Pope, the Emperour, King, Duke, or any other Prince under whom the Iewes live, and add's;] <hi>The King of kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him in his mercy, making him joyfull, and free him from all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and diſtreſſe. The King of kings, for his goodneſſe ſake, raiſe up and exalt his planetary ſtarre, and multiply his dayes over his Kingdom. The King of kings for his mercies ſake, put into his heart, and into the heart of his Counſellers, and thoſe that attend and adminiſter to him, that he may ſhow mercy unto us, and unto all the people of Iſraël. In his dayes and in our dayes, let Iudah be ſafe, and Iraë dwell ſecurely, and let the Redeemer come to Iraë; and ſo may it pleaſe God. Amen.</hi> Theſe are the very formalities ſet downe word for word, which the Iewes, by the command of God, received from the Talmud, do uſe in their prayers for Princes, under whoſe gouvernment they reſide. And therefore wiſe Princes are wont to baniſh from their Courts falſe rapports. And moſt wiſe <hi>R. Simon Ben-Iochai,</hi> in his excellent book called <hi>Zoar</hi> in Saraſa Pecudi, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, that <hi>it is a Tradition receaved from Heaven, that the Kings of the Nations of the world, Princes, Gouvernours, that protect the Iewes in this world, or do them any good, that the ſame ſhall enjoy certain degrees of glory, or eternall reward; as on the other ſide, they that do to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Iewes any harme, that they ſhall be puniſhed with ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular eternall puniſhment.</hi> As appeareth alſo out of Eſa. the laſt chapter.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the Fidelity of the Iewes towards their Gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours clearly prooved. Now, that no man may thinke that their baniſhment out of Spaigne and Portugal, proceeded from any ſuſpition or faults of theirs, I ſhall clearly rehearſe the reaſon of ſo ſudden a determination, and what the thoughts of many Chriſtian Princes have bene there-upon. The buſines was thus: Ferdinand and Iſabella, Gouvernours of Caſtile, having gained the Kingdome of Granada, of which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64987:12"/>they tooke poſſeſſion on the 5 of Ianuary, they reſolved to thruſt out all the Iewes that lived in their Kingdomes, and ſo on the laſt of March, they made an Edict in the ſame City, in which they expreſſed: <hi>That ſeeing the Iewes in their Countries drew many Chriſtians to turne Iewes, and eſpecially ſome Noble-men of their Kingdome of Andaluzia, that for this cauſe they baniſhed them under moſt heavy penalties, &amp;c.</hi> So that the cauſe of their baniſhment was not any diſloyalty at all.</p>
            <p>Now what amongſt many others in all Chriſtendom, one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Lawyer in Rome, and Oſorius an excellent and moſt elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Hiſtorian have thought, I ſhall here relate. In the year 1492 (ſaith the Lawyer) Ferdinand, called the Catholick, being King of Spaine, drove out of his Country all the Iewes that were living there from the time of the Babylonian and Roman Captivity, and were very rich in houſes and goods: and that upon pain, if they went not away within the terme of 6 moneths, that all their houſes and goods ſhould be confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto the Exchequer, which as we have ſaid, were very great. Whereupon they leaving the Kingdome of Caſtile, they went over many of them into Portugal, as being the neareſt place. In the year 1497, there being an Alliance contracted between the Kings of Caſtile and Portugal; the Iewes at the requeſt of the ſaid King Ferdinand, were baniſhed out of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal; but it being againſt the will of Emauël, King of Portugal, to have them baniſhed out of his Country, he reſolved to oblidge them to become Chriſtians, promiſing never to moleſt them, neither in Criminall matters, nor in the loſſe of their goods; and exempted them from many burdens and Tributs of the Kingdome. This Emanuël being dead, Iohn III. ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in his place in the Kingdome of Portugal, who being excited by others, ſaid, That what his Father Emanuë had done, concerning the not-troubling them, was of no valew, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64987:13"/>they lived not as was convenient, and that without the authority of the Pope of Rome, his father could not graunt any ſuch thing: for which cauſe he would that for thoſe that lived amiſh, there ſhould be proceeded againſt, as againſt the Mores in Caſtile: And ſending to Rome to diſanull the ſaid promiſes, it was not onely not graunted to him, but moreover they reprooved his appearance there, and praiſed and approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the promiſes made by his Father Emanuël to the Iewes, publiſhing a general pardon to all that were taken, which were about 1500, and they all were ſet free. Which Bull was granted by Clement VII. by the intervention of all the Conſiſtory of Cardinals. Afterwards the ſaid king Iohn ſent once againe to deſire the former Licence with ſo many replications and tripli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, that at length the Pope granted it: But a few dayes after it was revoked againe with a generall Pardon to all that were taken, which were 12000, with ſuch a determination, that the ſame Licence ſhould never be granted, as being againſt all right and reaſon. This troubled Don Iohn the King very much, and withall the Cardinal his brother, who came in theſe laſt dayes to be King of Portugal himſelf. Great Paul III. of the houſe of Farneſia, ſucceeding to Clement the VII. there was a requeſt tendred to the Pope for power to bring in the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition into this Kingdome: The Pope would not grant it, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: He could not, and that it was a thing againſt reaſon and Iuſtice, but on the contrary confirmed the promiſes made by the King Don Emanuël, his Father; and pardonned all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents ſince the time of violence unto that day. Don Iohn ſeeing this, ſent an Embaſſadour meerly for that buſines to the Pope, but could obtaine nothing at all: for which cauſe King Iohn reſolved to entreat the Emperour Charles the V. than paſſing for Rome, as Conquerour over the Turks, having wonn Tunis and Goleta, that in this his Triumph he would
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64987:13"/>take occaſion to deſire this favour from the Pope, that the King of Portugal might ſet up the Inquiſition in his Kingdome, it being an old cuſtome that thoſe that triumphed, ſhould aske ſomething of the Pope that they moſt deſired. The Emperour than having deſired this, the Pope anſwered him, that he could not do it by reaſon of the agreement made, and the promiſes of the King Don Emanuël; which he had found by an Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Nuntio in Portugal in the year 1497, at which time the Iewes were forced and compelled to become Chriſtians. The Emperour replied, Let that ſinne fall on him, and the Prince his ſonne, the Apoſtolicall ſeat ſhall be free from it. So the Pope granted it; becauſe the Emperour Charles the V. was brother in law to King Don Iohn of Portugal; and beſides they treated at that time to enter further in affinity, and to marry their children, which ſince was effected. After Paul the III. granted this, there was a new Pardon given in generall to all that were taken unto that time, amounting the Number unto 1800. But the King refuſing to obey the Pardon, and to free the Priſonners, the Pope tooke it very ill, and ſent for this one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſines for his Nuntio, one Monſegnor Monte Paliciano, who ſince was Cardinal of the Church of Rome. And the King for all this not obeying, the Pope made the Nuntio to ſix the Pardon upon the doores of the Cathedral Churches, and the Nuntio cauſed the Priſons to be opened, and there were ſet free about 1800 priſonners. He that ſollicited this buſines at Rome, was one Seignor Duarte de Paz, a Cavallier of the Order of St. Iohn: whom to ſearch out there were appointed at Rome ten men diſguiſed; theſe having found him, gave him fifteen wounds, and left him for dead: thus wounded, he was carried to the houſe of Seignor Philip Eſtrozi: This being reported to the Pope, Paul the III. he cauſed him to be carried to the Caſtle of S. Angelo, where he gave order to have him nobly cured.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64987:14"/>That ſame Seignor was by the Pope, by all the Cardinals and the whole Court in great reſpect. At the ſame time that this man was hurt, the Emperour Charles the V. was at Rome with his Army. On the time when he began to treat of this buſines with Clement the VII. ſeeing the Kings importunity, he made a Bull and gave licence to all the Portugals of that Nation of the Iewes, that they might go and live in the Church-Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and whoſoever will come in the ſaid Dominions, that he ſhall have freedom to live, as at the firſt, in his Iewiſh profeſſion, and that at no time they ſhould be enquired into, but after the ſame manner as they were wont to live in Portugal, ſo they ſhould live there. The ſaid Bull paſſed all the Conſiſtory; and being confirmed and received by the ſaid Portugals, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan ſome of them to depart to live in Ancona, being a ſea-port more commodious then others: which being known by the King and Cardinal of Portugal, they cauſed to be proclaimed in all the Kingdome, that upon paine of death, and loſſe of all their goods, no man ſhould dare depart the Kingdome. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being dead, in his place ſucceeded (as we have ſaid) Pope Paul the III. who confirmed the ſame Priviledges: Afterwards in the year 1550. Paul the III. died, and Iulius the III. ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, who ratified the fore-mentioned Priviledges given by his Praedeceſſours, and the whole Apoſtolike Seat inviolably. In thoſe times there were many Doctors that wrote on this matter, amongſt whom the chiefeſt were Alciat, and the Cardinal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſius in 2 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 <hi>parte Conſiliorum pro Chriſtianis noviter converſis;</hi> ſhewing by reaſon and law, that conſidering they were forced and not converted willingly, that they had not fallen nor do fall under any Cenſure. Theſe reaſons being conſidered of by the Princes of Italy, they graunted likewiſe the ſame Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges: viz. Coſmo the Great; Duke of Florence, and Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules, Duke of Ferrare, and within few yeares Emanuël Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64987:14"/>Duke of Savoye; and were by all his ſucceſſours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. In the yeare 1492, when they were baniſhed from Caſtile, we read in the Chronicles of that Kingdome, that the Lords of that place did complain that their Cities and Townes were deſtroyed and dis-inhabitated; and had they beleeved any ſuch thing, that they would have oppoſed the Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and would never have given their conſent to it. That was the cauſe, that Don Emanuël of Portugal, ſeeing on the one ſide apparent dommage, ſhould he let them depart his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and on the other ſide, not being able to breake his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to the King of Caſtile, he cauſed them to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to the Faith, upon paine of Death, that they ſhould not depart out of his Dominions. The Catholiq King was blamed of all Chriſtian Princes, and eſpecially by the Senate of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, (as Marcus Antonius Sabellicus doth write) for having baniſhed a Nation ſo profitable to the Publicq and Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good, without any kinde of pretence. And ſo the Parlement of Paris likewiſe did extreamly wonder at ſuch a determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And truely good reaſon there was to wonder; for we ſee ſince, what the Senat of Venice hath done, who never deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berats or puts into execution any thing, without great judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: having the advantage of all Republicqs in their gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and leaving behinde them the Romans, Carthage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Athenians, and moſt learned Lacedemonians; and that Parlement of Paris, which in the gouvernment of affaires was alwayes moſt prudent. Moſt of thoſe that were baniſhed paſſed to the Levant, who were embraced by the Ottoman-familly, al the ſucceeding Kings wondring at it, that the Spanjards, who make profeſſion to be a politiq Nation, ſhould drive out of their Kingdoms ſuch a people. Moreover Sultan Bajazet, and Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Soliman, received them exceeding well, the coming of the Iewes to them being very acceptable: and ſo did likewiſe all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64987:15"/>their ſucceſſours, conſidering of how great a profit and benefit their reſiding in their dominions was. And in the yeare 1555. Paul the IV. being choſen Pope of Rome, who before was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Cardinal de Chieſi, an intimate to the Cardinal of Portugal, cauſed the Iewes to be held in Ancona, and other places of the Church, according to the Priviledges graunted to them by the Popes, his Predeceſſeurs in the name of the Apoſtolical Roman ſeat. Licurgus, Solon and Draco, and all Founders of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, gave counſell that ſtrangers ought to be loved and much made of, as in the Diſcourſes of <hi>Se. in 7 de Legibus de Rep.</hi> is amply to be ſeen. And by the Divine Law (as Moſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth us) we ought not to trouble a ſtranger, but he ſayes, <hi>Remember you were ſtrangers in the Land of Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſumma, to the ſame purpoſe might be brought many other and more powerfull reaſons, but becauſe they are out of our conſideration, we paſſe them over. And here to declare ſome particulars, worthy to be known for adviſe and exemple, that befell our Nation in thoſe bitter baniſhments; part whereof Hieronymus Oſorius recites more at large, in the firſt of his elegant two Bookes de Rebus Emanuëlis. The firſt title he giveth to thoſe miſerable ſucceſſes, is this, which he puts for a Poſtil in the margent of his booke, <hi>Iudaeorum Liberi per vim ad Chriſtianiſmum pertracti:</hi> and than rehearſes, how that in the yeare 1496 the King decreed, that all the Iewes and Mores, that dwelt in his Kingdome, and would not become Chriſtians, ſhould depart his Dominions in a ſhort time; which being paſt, all that ſhould be found in his Kingdome, ſhould looſe their liberty, and become ſlaves to the King. The time being now at hand (as Oſorius proceeds) in which the Iewes, that would not turne Chriſtians, were to depart the Kingdome, and all of them as many as they were, had with all their power provided, and taken a firme reſolution to be gone: which the King
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64987:15"/>ſeeing; and not able to endure it, thought upon a buſines (as he ſaith) <hi>facto quidem iniquam &amp; injuſtam,</hi> which to do was realy wicked and unjuſt, and that was to command that all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Iſraëlites, that were not above 14 yeares old, ſhould be taken out of the power of their owne Parents; and when they had them, they ſhould force them to become Chriſtians; a new thing that could not be done without a wonderfull al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of their minds: for it was (as Oſorius ſpeakes) a horrid and miſerable ſpectacle, to ſee the tender Infants wreſtled out of the arms and breſts of their lamenting mothers, to dragge along their poore fathers that held them faſt, and to give them many wounds and blows to draw them out of their handes; to hear their cryes that aſcend to heaven, their groanes, lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and complaints every-where; ſo that this cruelty was the cauſe, that many of thoſe diſtreſſed Fathers threw their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into wells, and others killed themſelves with their owne hands, that they might not ſee ſo bitter a thing with their eyes. The cruelty of Emanuël ended not here, but going on with compulſion and revilings, gave cauſe to his owne Chronogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher to make the ſecond title or poſtil, with theſe words; <hi>Vis &amp; Dolus Iudaeis illata:</hi> That is, The force and deceit uſed towards the Iewes. And ſo he goes on, declaring how he had promiſed in the condition they had made, that he would aſſigne them three Ports in his Kingdome to embarque at, viz. Liſbon, Setu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, and Puerto: and nevertheleſſe he forbad them afterwards to embarque themſelves in any place but Liſbon: for which cauſe all the Iewes of the Kingdome came to that City, from whence beſides a thouſand moleſtations and extortions, he drove them (as Vaſquo ſaith) as ſheep in the ſtalls, and there forced their afflicted bodies to counterfeit, that which their ſoules and thoughts never meant nor approoved of. Works, of which his owne Chronologer ſaith, <hi>Fuit hoc quidem neque ex Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64987:16"/>neque ex Religione factum.</hi> That is, This was done neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, nor Religion. Let men of clear minde, and free from paſſion conſider for Gods ſake, if ſuch violences can worke any good impreſſion or character in men: or what Law, either Humain or Divine, National or Moderne, can beare, that the ſoules of men (which the Moſt High hath created free). be forced to beleeve what they beleeve not, and to love what they hate? This cruelty was reprooved and cenſured of many Princes of the world and learned men. And his owne Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger reprehends it with a new poſtil, and ſpeakes freely; <hi>Regis in Iudaeos facinorum reprehenſio.</hi> That is, A cenſure of the Kinges wickednes againſt the Iewes. Truely with juſt reaſon doth Oſorius call the workes, which the King did unto us, <hi>Iniquities and injuſtices, deceitfull violences, and wicked attempts:</hi> And ſo goes on, reprooving them with moſt elegant Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Further what happened to the Iewes under other Princes in other Kingdomes and Countries, is notorious and enough known to all the world, and therefore not neceſſary here to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. So farre concerning their Banniſhment.</p>
            <p>Now, I will not conceale to ſay, but that alwayes there have bene found ſome calumniators, that endeavouring to make the Nation infamous, laid upon them <hi>three moſt falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports,</hi> as if <hi>they were dangerous to the Goods, the Lives,</hi> and withall to <hi>the very Soules of the Natives.</hi> They urge againſt them their <hi>uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> the <hi>ſlaying of infants</hi> to celebrate their Paſſe-over, and the <hi>inducing Chriſtians to become Iewes.</hi> To all which I ſhall anſwer briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As for <hi>uſury,</hi> ſuch dealing is not the eſſentiall property of the Iewes, for though in Germany there be ſome indeed that practiſe uſury; yet the moſt part of them that live in Turky, Italy, Holland and Hamburg, being come out of Spaigne, they hold it infamous to uſe it; and ſo with a very ſmall profit of 4.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64987:16"/>or 5 per Cent, as Chriſtians themſelves do, they put their money ordinarily in Banco: for to lay out their money without any profit, was commanded onely toward their brethren of the ſame Nation of the Iewes; but not to any other Nation. And however by this Charity is not hurt: for it ſtands in good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that every one ſhould gaine and get ſome advantage with his money, to ſuſtaine his owne life: and when any one to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his own wants, doth take ſome cours of marchandiſe, by which he hopes to gaine by other mens moneys taken up on truſt, 't is no inhumanity to reckon and take from him uſe: For as no man is bound to give his goods to an other; ſo is he not bound to let it out, but for his owne occaſions and profit, and not to leave himſelf deſtitute of the profit he could make of the moneys. Onely this muſt be done with moderation, that the uſury be not biting and exorbitant, which the Chriſtians themſelves uſe, amongſt themſelves; as even in the Mounts of Piety at Padua, Vicenza and Verona is to be ſeen, where they take 6 par Cent, and elſewere yet much more. This in no manner can be called Robbery, but is with conſent and will of the Contracter; and the ſame Sacred Scripture, which allows uſury with him that is not of the ſame Religion, forbids abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely the robbing of all men, whatſoever Religion they be of, In our Law it is a greater ſinne to rob or defraud a ſtranger, than if I did it to one of my owne profeſſion: becauſe a Iew is bound to ſhew his charity to all men: for he hath a precept, not to abhorre an Idumean, nor an Egyptian; and that he ſhall love and protect a ſtranger that comes to live in his land. If notwithſtanding there be ſome that do contrary to this, they do it not as Iewes ſimply, but as wicked Iewes, as amongſt all nations there are found generally ſome Uſurers.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64987:17"/>2. As for <hi>killing of the yong children of Chriſtians;</hi> it is an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible truth what is reported of the Negros of Guinea and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zil, that if they ſee any miſerable man that hath eſcaped from the danger of the ſea, or hath fallen or ſuffered any kind of ill-fortune, or Shipwrake, they perſecute and vex him ſo much the more, ſaying, <hi>God curſe thee.</hi> And wee that live not amongſt the Blacke-moors and wild-men, but amongſt the white and civilized people of the world, yet wee find this an ordinary cours, that men are very prone to hate and deſpiſe him that hath ill fortune; and on the other ſide, to make much of thoſe whom fortune doth favour. Hereof the Chriſtians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have good experience; for during the times of their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and perſecution under the Roman Empire, they were falſly ſlandred of divers Emperours and tyrannicall Princes. Nero accuſed them, that they had ſet Rome on fire; Others, that they were Witches and Conjurers; and others againe that they ſlew their children to celebrate their Ceremonies, as wee find in divers Authors. Even ſo likewiſe it is with the Iewiſh Nation, that now is diſperſed and afflicted, though they have moneys: There is no ſlander nor calumny that is not caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, even the very ſame ancient ſcandall that was caſt of old upon the innocent Chriſtians, is now laid upon the Iewes. Whereas the whole world may eaſely perceive, it is but a meer ſlander, ſeeing it is known that at this day, out of Ieruſalem, no ſacrifice nor blood is in any uſe by them, even that blood which is found in an Egg is forbidden them, how much more mans blood? More-over I could produce divers memorable exemples which out in our owne times in Araguza to a Iew: how he was accuſed of this ſame wickednes, and not confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, how they impriſoned him betwixt two walls, and being in that diſtreſſe, how he cited before God all the Iudges to anſwer there for what they did; and how within a year after,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64987:17"/>many of the Iudges died, and thoſe that lived, fearing the like might befall them, and looſe their lives, ſet him free: But I muſt not be too prolix; it may ſuffice to ſay, that by the Pope himſelf it was defined in full Counſell the accuſation to be falſe; and ſo likewiſe judged all the Princes of Italy; as alſo Alphonſo the Wiſe, King of Spaine, and that it was onely a neere invention to drinke the blood, and to ſwallow up the goods of the harmleſſe Iewes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As for the <hi>third</hi> Point, I ſay, that although Ferdinand and Iſabell, giving colour to ſo indiſcreet a determination, ſaid, that they induced the Nobles to become Iewes, yet true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this cannot be ſaid, but by ſome falſe informations. For if ſo be, amongſt thoſe difficulties and impoſſibilities, it may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that ſome of the Sect of the Papiſts, of a better minde, embrace the Iewiſh Religion; it cannot therefore be preſumed, that they were induced thereunto by the Iewes; ſeeing the Iewes do not entice any man to profeſſe their Law: But if any man of his own free-will come to them, they by their rites and Ceremonies are obliged to make proofe of them, whether they come for any temporall intereſt, and to perſuade them to looke well to themſelves what they do: that the Law unto which they are to ſubmit themſelves, is of many precepts; and doth oblige the tranſgreſſor to many ſore puniſhments. And ſo we follow the example of Nahomi, cited in the Sacred Scripture, who did not perſuade Ruth to go along with her; but ſaid firſt to her: <hi>Orpa thy ſiſter returned to her Nation and her. Gods; go thou and follow her.</hi> But Ruth continuing conſtant, then at length ſhee received her.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, the Iewes indeed have reaſon to take care for their owne preſervation; and therefore will not go about by ſuch wayes to make themſelves odious to Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, under whoſe Dominions they live.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:64987:18"/>Now, becauſe I beleeve, that with a good conſcience I have diſcharged our Nation of the Iewes of thoſe three ſlanders or calumnies, as elſewhere I have more at large written about it; I conceive I may from thoſe two qualities, of Profitablenes and Fidelity conclude, that ſuch a Nation ought to be well entertained, and alſo beloved and protected generally of all. The more, conſidering they are called in the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Sonnes of God; and 't is ſaid by all the Prophets, that they who ſhall wrong them, ſhall be moſt ſeverely puniſhed; and that he that toucheth them, toucheth the apple of Gods eye. And at leaſt, it was alwayes the opinion of Auguſtine, as he made it appear in his works <hi>Libr. de Doctrina Chriſtianâ cap.</hi> 28. where he ſaith, <hi>Quod omnes homines aequè diligendi ſunt.</hi> That all men are equally to be beloved.</p>
            <p>Now, having prooved the two former Points, I could adde a third, viz. of the Nobility of the Iewes: but becauſe that Point is enough known amongſt all Chriſtians, as lately yet it hath bene moſt worthily and excellently ſhewed and deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in a certain Booke, called, <hi>The Glory of the Iehudah and Iſraël,</hi> dedicated to our Nation by that worthy Chriſtian Miniſter <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Henry Ieſſey,</hi> (1653. in Dutch) where this matter is ſet out at large: And by <hi>M. Edw. Nicholas</hi> Gentleman, in his Booke, called, <hi>An Apologie for the Honorable Nation of the Iewes, and all the Sons of Iſraël</hi> (1648. in Engliſh.) Therefore I will here for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, and reſt on that ſaying of our King Salomon, the wiſeſt on earth, <hi>Let another mans mouth praiſe, thee, and not thine owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64987:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
